翻譯:桌面王(Netpilot)
沙漠女王
第一次世界大戰加速了統治中東
長達五個世紀的土耳其帝國的滅亡
殖民地遭到瓜分...
自付的土耳其帝國最終不存在了
Assuming the Ottoman Empire finally becomes defunct,
俄國會取得達達尼爾海峽，與他們非常接近
Russia would get the Dardanelles, the portion closest to them,
至於意大利，在大陸群島上
and the Italians, the islands of mainland.
- 那法國沒意見嗎？ - 法國對什麼事情都有意見
- The French had no problem with that? - The French have problems with everything.
那是他們的天性
That's their nature.
多大的份額？
And the big portions?
一旦控制了敘利亞和黎巴嫩，之後就容易多了
Once I conceeded the control over Syria and Lebanon to them it got easier.
讓我們聽聽你的想法
Let us read your mind.
丘吉爾先生，你真的想讓黎巴嫩加入大英帝國嗎？
Mr Churchill, do you really want Lebanon for the British Empire?
上千年來的混亂局面，沒人能理順
It's a mess grown in a 1,000 years that no one will ever disentangle.
敘利亞會造成很大的問題
Syria might pose a bigger problem.
遜尼派教徒， 什葉派教徒， 德魯士，基督教徒都相互敵對
Sunni, Shiite, Alawis, Druze, Christian, all at each other's throats.
北方還有庫爾德人，讓法國去對付庫爾德人
And up North, the Kurds. Let the French deal with the Kurds.
或者，讓法國試著去對付庫爾德人
Or let the French try to deal with the Kurds.
他們會失敗的
And let them fail.
我知道你這些情報是從哪裡來的
I know where all our intelligence comes from.
你的意思是說...從一個女人那裡？
Are you trying to say... from the woman?
從那個女人那裡？
From that woman?
喝了雞尾酒後的小錯誤
Petty rivalries only after cocktails.
現在，對於我們
Now, to us.
戰區B，是我們的控制範圍
Zone B: our area of influence.
我經過和法國，巴格達，巴士拉，科威特較量
I wrestle from the French Baghdad, Bazra, Kuwait.
這些現在都由我們直接控制了
This will now be under our direct control.
那麼我們如何定義邊界呢？
And how do we delineate the borders?
- 那是早晚的事 - 不
- That we'll formalize later. - No.
現在就是時候了，必須是
This is the moment. It has to be now.
我們的問題在這兒，南部
Our issues start down here, in the South.
現在還是模糊的紅色虛線
Now it's just a vague red dotted line.
- 沙特阿拉伯是我們的麻煩 - 十足的惡棍
- We have a problem with Ibn Saud. - The scoundrel.
事實上，我們有兩個問題
In fact we have two problems.
首先，他想讓阿拉伯半島分離成為他的獨立國家
Firstly, he wants the whole Arabia as a separate country for himself.
混蛋
The bastard.
其次，他希望邊界不那麼明確
And secondly, he wants a flexible border.
他的一個部族，夏天要去北方放牧
One of his tribes is moving North for the summer pastures.
那裡什麼都沒有，只有沙漠
There are no bloody pastures. There's only sand.
他希望邊界...
And he wants a border...
主要是那些遊牧民族，不是武裝自衛隊
according to the movement of people, not territorial.
中東不好搞定啊
East is not fly.
誰最瞭解這些部族？
Who knows best about tribes?
血統，成員情況，對抗行為
Lineages, affiliations, rivalries.
誰最瞭解貝都因人？
Who knows best about Bedouin tribes?
誰能統治他們？
And who is going to rule over all this?
我們在討論未來的國王
We are talking to potential future kings.
誰認識志願者？ 誰最瞭解？
Who knows the candidates? Who knows them best?
那個女人，格特魯德
The woman. Gertrude.
格特魯德是誰？
Gertrude who?
- 格特魯德 貝爾 - 一個小蕩婦
- Gertrude Bell. - A silly bitch.
總是喋喋不休的，自付的，熱情的
It's a chattering windbag of conceited, gushing,
胸大的女人
heavychested manwoman,
到處遊走的，四處閒逛的傢伙
a globetrotting, rumpwagging, blethering ass.
格特魯德
Gertrude.
十二年前
- 格特魯德 貝爾，看著我 - 媽媽，不要
- Gertrude, look at me. - Mother, don't.
- 什麼？ - 不要告訴我這些禮儀
- What? - Don't tell me how to behave.
我必須這樣做
I'm afraid I'm going to, anyway.
- 你要笑出來 - 是的，媽媽
- You will smile. - Yes, mother.
你不要因為你的聰明才智嚇壞年輕男人
You will not scare the young men with your intelligence.
我怎麼能做到呢？我又不能沉默不語
How do I do that? I cannot play dumb.
只是...聽聽他們說話，微笑就行了
Just... listen to what they have to say and smile.
那太難了
That will be hard.
- 格特魯德... - 我喜歡它
- Gertrude... - I love it.
我喜歡它
I love it.
- 之後呢？ - 你的意思是在獅子後面？
- And then? - You mean after the lion?
- 是的 - 然後我開槍射殺了大象
- Yes. - Then I shot an elephant.
這些都發生在蘇丹南部？
And all of this was in the South Sudan?
不，我的打獵場所改在了肯尼亞
No, my hunting party had moved to Kenya by then.
天那，很好的旅行路線！
God, what that a safari!
我猜你不僅僅射殺了大象
I would guess you didn't shoot just one elephant.
首先是犀牛，然後是獅子還有兩隻大象
First a rhino, then a lion, and then two elephant bulls.
那麼非洲還有大象嗎？
Are there any elephants left in Africa?
你是什麼意思呢，女士？
You meaning what, young lady?
格特魯德...
Gertrude...
我很想和你出去
I would love to elope with you.
去哪兒？ 巴黎，印度？
Where to? Paris, India?
埃及？
The pyramids?
外面有個穀倉
Out there, there is a barn.
你的意思是在乾草上？
You mean hay?
我們離開幾分鐘沒人會注意到的
Nobody would notice if we left for a few minutes.
你的意思是出去通姦
You mean for fornication. Straightforward.
是的
Absolutely.
- 就像是在地裡的牲口那樣？ - 是的
- Like the cattle in the field? - Absolutely.
阿諾德 朗西，我都不瞭解你
Arnold Runcie, I barely know you.
- 但你看起來像頭牛一樣 - 是的
- But you seem to like cows. - Absolutely.
你有多少女人？
How many do you have?
在紐卡斯爾有大約800人
Near Newcastle I have 800 Herefordshire.
北邊，蘇格蘭，大約2000
Up North, in Scotland, 2,000.
- 愛神？ - 愛神，是的
- Angus? - Angus. Yes.
阿拉丁愛神啊
Black Angus.
貝爾小姐，感謝你的表揚
Miss Bell, thank you for the honor.
我在這兒，海文斯特先生
Over here, Mr. Havenhurst.
在你左邊呢
Over here to your left.
我很抱歉
I'm so sorry.
我的天啊！
Dear God!
還不如地震算了
Send me an earthquake, please.
我受不了了
I can't take it.
我感覺太受束縛了
I feel so domesticated.
- 簡直令人窒息  - 格特魯德，我能說什麼呢？
- It's stifling to me. - Gertrude, what am I suppoed to say?
我要說。我們不能讓你去牛津
I can say it. We should never have allowed you to go to Oxford.
但是，親愛的，她是僅有的四個女人之一
But dear, she's one of only four women
學習歷史，並且拿到了最高的學位
to study history and graduate with the highest honors.
一個年輕的出自豪門的未婚女子，不應該...
A young unmarried woman from a good family should not...
不應該在沒有人陪伴的情況下隨便出門
Should not be allowed out on the streets without a chaperon.
- 格特魯德，你能坐下嗎？  - 不，我不想坐著
- Gertrude, would you please sit down? - No, I don't want to sit down.
親愛的，我是一直支持你的
Darling, I have always supported you.
我看著你長大的
I watched you climb sharp, high rocks.
我們不要忘記，你奶奶由於你的任性離開了人世
Let us not forget the string of nannies who quit because of your willfulness.
那又怎樣
Well, so what.
你還記得那時候，你爬到公園裡的樹上嗎？
Do you remember that time when you climbed that tall tree in the park?
你的背後帶著個巨大的罩子
And you had a very large lamp shade on your back.
是的，我記得
Yes, I remember that.
你只有五歲，你都已經能閱讀
You were only 5, you were already reading voraciously.
有人給你的里昂納多 達芬奇速寫集了
Somebody stupidly showed you Leonardo da Vinci's sketchbook.
- 我還記得帶降落傘的傢伙 - 誰會需要降落傘呢？
- I remember the one with the parachute. - Who ever would need a parachute?
所有人多需要降落傘
Everyone. Everyone needs a parachute.
這可比你腳崴了更讓我擔心
It probably hurt me more than you when you broke your ankle.
我不要想那些事情了，讓我今天感到很難過
I don't like to think about it, it hurts me even today.
讓我出去吧
Get me out of here, please.
求你們了，讓我出去吧！
Please, please, get me out of here!
印度，阿拉伯，任何地方，求你們了！
India, Arabia, anywhere. Please !
你知道...
You know...
你不在我們身邊怎麼都會讓我擔心的
However how much it hurts me when you're not around,
我們決定讓你出去
we are going to have to get you out of here.
去哪兒？
Where?
德黑蘭如何？
What about Tehran?
大使館
The embassy.
一個月後
我要來介紹格特魯德小姐
I'm going to introduce Gertrude now.
是時候了。把你的杯子給我一下？ 謝謝
It's introduction time. Give me your glass for a moment? Thank you.
大家好
Excellencies.
給。女士們先生們，大家過來
Here. Ladies and gentlemen, come forward.
大家過來，謝謝
Come forward. Thank you.
我很高興給大家介紹格特魯德 洛西恩 貝爾小姐
I'd like to introduce Gertrude Lowthian Bell to you.
她是一顆閃耀的新星
She is a brilliant young scholar.
她是我的外甥女
And I am blessed to call her my niece.
她實際上是我夫人瑪麗的妹妹的女兒
She is actually the daughter of my wife Mary's sister.
我們愛她
And we love her.
我確信，你會讓她很我們在一起非常開心的
And I'm sure you will make her stay with us a wonderful experience.
言歸正傳，我的妻子
As to the return of my dear wife,
我的孩子，我放蕩的生活結束了
boys, the wildlife is over.
再也不允許騎馬進入餐廳
No more riding on horseback into our dining room.
再也不允許在我們整齊的草坪上酗酒
No more drunken orgies on our well-groomed British lawn.
再也不允許拯救那些陷入困境的少女
No more rescues of damsels in distress.
再也不允許在公眾場合
And no more public display
對維多利亞女王不敬
of the wildest irreverance towards our beloved Queen Victoria.
我認為我們應該花些時間
Who, I think, needs to spend time here
引導她從過分拘謹的帝國生活中走出來
to lean her from her grand design of a prudish empire.
敬大英帝國！
To the British Empire!
敬伊朗
And to Persia.
一個具有5000年歷史的國家
The country of 5,000 years of poetry.
為什麼我的酒杯空了？
Why is my glass empty?
我的香檳呢？
Where is the champagne?
這裡的感覺...我無法相信
The sense... I can't believe it.
- 還有小鳥 - 南丁格爾
- And birds. - Nightingale.
當我夜裡抱著枕頭哭泣的時候，她總讓我很高興
When I cry at night into my pillow, she always makes me feel happy.
她？ 我覺得只有男人才唱歌
She? I think it's only the males who sing.
- 別寵壞它 - 我很抱歉，弗洛倫斯...
- Don't spoil it. - I'm sorry, Flo...
你好
Hello.
我是亨利 卡多根
I'm Henry Cadogan.
- 我是... - 亨利是大使的秘書
- I am... - Henry is the secretary of the Embassy.
事實上，我是他的第三個秘書
Actually, I'm only the third secretary.
貝爾小姐，我很高興你能來女王統治下的大使館
Ms. Bell, I welcome you to the embassy of Her Majesty the Queen.
過分拘謹的陛下
A prudish majesty.
我被指派做為你的助理
I've been officially assigned to be your guardian
來招待你，所以...
and to entertain you, so...
如果你有任何需求，請來找我
If there's anything you need at all, please let me know.
我會的
I will do that.
亨利
Henry.
亨利，表演一下你的戲法
Henry, please show us your trick shots.
弗洛倫斯，桌子有人在用啊
Florence, the table is not even free.
求你了
Please.
不，我不是馬戲團的表演者
No, I'm not a circus performer.
他有兩個不可思議的戲法
It has two unbelievable trick shots.
表演一下「月球軌道」
Show us your "Orbit the Moon".
弗洛倫斯，這裡是大使館啊
Florence, it's embarrassing.
- 你的第二個戲法是什麼？ - 是「青蛙跳」
- What's your second trick shot? - The "Frog Leap".
亨利，表演一下撲克牌戲法
Henry, show us your card trick.
他撲克牌戲法棒極了
He has the greatest of card trick.
- 真的嗎？ - 求你了
- Really? - Please.
弗洛倫斯，這是個愚蠢的戲法，不！
Florence, it's a silly trick. No!
走吧
Come, come.
貝爾小姐，我可以建議把你住所的床
Ms. Bell, may I suggest at the residency,
放在屋頂上，面對天空嗎
you put your bed out on the roof under the sky.
我很喜歡夜裡的星星
I do love the stars at night.
但是，我還要給你掛上蚊帳
Although I'll have to put out the mosquito netting for you.
蚊子太可怕了
The mosquitoes are awful.
拉塞爾斯小姐，我們打擾到你了嗎？
Mrs. Lascelles, are we not boring you?
沒有
No.
哦，不，沒有
Oh, no. No, no, no.
弗洛倫斯，弗洛倫斯，過來一下好嗎？
Florence. Florence, will you please come over?
現在？
Now?
新來的意大利大使有禮物給你
The new Italian ambassador has a present for you.
- 亨利，我一會兒回來 - 亨利
- Henry, I should come right back. - Hurray.
這裡就像是「野獸花園」
It's like "The Beast's Garden".
這裡有花，感覺像是一個完美的夢魘
It's a perfect nightmare of flowers and sens.
卡多根先生，你能告訴我上面的碑文寫的是什麼嗎？
Mr. Cadogan, do you by any chance know what this inscription says?
好的
Yes.
是波斯語
It's in Farsi.
來自中世紀
But a medieval form of it.
你能讀一下嗎？
Can you read it?
「我播種的智慧的種子」
"With them, the seed of wisdom did I sow
「我親手勞動栽培它」
"and with my own hand labour'd it to grow."
「這是我得到的所有收貨」
"And this was all the harvest that I reap'd
「我喜歡水還有風」
"I came like water and like wind I go."
貝爾小姐，你精通詩歌？
Miss Bell, you know poetry?
- 你知道奧瑪 開陽嗎 - 是的，知道
- You know Omar Khayyam. - Yes.
我想學習他的語言
I want to learn his language.
親愛的媽媽
Mother dearest,
我今天有機會用外交郵包
I'm using the opportunity to send you this
給你發送這封信
With today's diplomatic pouch.
我度過了很珍貴的第一周，而且還學習了一些波斯語
My first week has been most precious and I have started to learn Farsi
可以閱讀一些詩句
in order to read the poets in their original.
在大使館工作的卡多根先生，幫助了我很多
Mr. Cadogan, who works at the embassy, is very helpful in this.
他很彬彬有禮，聰明也很博學
He is agreeable, intelligent, well-read,
照看我們，弗洛倫斯和我，他很擅長
looking after us, Florence and me, as his special property.
我喜歡他
I like him.
他邀請我們今天和他一起騎馬
He's invited us to ride with him today."
- 但是，亨利，你不能騎馬 - 我可以的
- But Henry, you can't ride. - Yes, I can.
掉下來怎麼辦？
What if you fall?
- 那都是巧合 - 你會受傷的
- It happens to the best. - You will get hurt.
我不喜歡騎馬
I don't like you to ride.
- 你為什麼不一起來？ - 我害怕騎馬
- Why don't you join us? - I'm afraid of horses.
再見
Bye.
貝爾小姐，這裡是我最喜歡的地方
Miss Bell, this is my favorite place in all of the countryside.
冬季過後，水位上漲的非常高
After the winter, when the water level is very high,
牧羊人游泳過來為了夏天的牧草
and the shepherds swim their flocks down here for the summer pasture.
有時候，有上千隻綿羊
Sometimes, a thousand of sheep.
牧羊人在羊群中間游來游去
And the shepherds swim among them on these inflated goat skins.
- 是的，我以前見過 - 是嗎？
- Yes, I've seen that. - Have you?
在巴爾倫城
In Babylonian reliefs.
他們這樣做有4000年歷史了
They were doing it 4,000 years ago.
- 他們至今還這樣做 - 非常特別
- They still do. - It's extraordinary.
有時候我還爬到那裡
Sometimes I go up there.
我是相當不錯的爬山愛好者
I'm a fairly good mountain climber,
但是你是怎麼上去的呢？
but how for God's sake do you get up there?
我告訴你，這很容易的
I must confess it's pretty easy.
你繞道後面，然後爬上去
You walk around the back and go up.
為什麼？
Why?
為什麼你去那裡呢？
Why do you go there?
我去是因為我很孤獨
I go when I'm lonely.
我很孤獨
I get very lonely.
格特魯德
Gertrude.
- 有事嗎？ - 一封信
- Yes? - A letter.
- 我的信？- 不，是給亨利的
- A letter for me? - No, for Henry.
- 你的意思是給卡多根先生的？ - 是的，亨利
- You mean Mr. Cadogan? - Yes, Henry.
你能把信給他嗎？
Could you please hand him this letter?
你為什麼不自己給他？
Why don't you give it to him yourself?
我不能
I cannot.
為什麼不能呢？
Why can't you?
格特魯德，女人和女人之間的事情，你不能告訴任何人？
Gertrude, from woman to woman, you won't say anything?
- 我不會說 - 不和任何人說
- No, I won't. - To no one?
甚至靈魂，我保證
Not a soul. I promise.
自從去年，我的意思是一年，兩個月，11天...
Ever since last year. I mean since one year, two months and 11 days...
什麼？
What?
我不得不說...
I have had...
我愛上亨利了
a passion for Henry.
他今天說什麼了嗎？ 他提及到我嗎？
What did he say to you today? Did he mention me today?
沒有，我們只是談論起牧羊人
No, we just talked about shepherds.
你為什麼不自己把信給卡多根先生呢？
Why can't you give Mr. Cadogan your letter?
我就是不能
I just can't.
我給他信的話，會導致很多流言蜚語的
And I sending him letters by mail might cause gossip upon its arrival.
信？
Letters?
我給他寫了202封信了
I wrote him 202.
太可怕了
It's terrible.
我不能去送
I can't send them.
親愛的弗洛倫斯
Sweet Florence, my darling.
你知道，我會為你做一切事情的
You know I'd do anything for you.
但是我不能傷害你的心
But I cannot fight the battles of your heart.
親愛的父親
Father dearest,
我不知道從哪裡說起
I do not know where to begin.
東方就像是一個夢
The Orient is like a prolonged dream.
嬸嬸把我各個方面照顧的都非常好
I am being taken care of wonderfully by Auntie, and for all the rest
卡多根先生是個很不錯的嚮導和助理
Mr. Cadogan is a fine guide and guardian.
他照顧弗洛倫斯和我
He takes care of Florence and me.
他帶我們去看市場上有意思的東西
He shows us lovely things from the bazaars.
我們需要他，他就會出現
He's always there when we want him.
我們不需要他就會離開
And never when we don't.
快點
Hurry.
謝謝你帶我們來這裡
Yes. Thank you for bringing us.
你看，他們真的吃羊頭
You see, they really eat the heads here.
是啊？
Do they?
- 好吃嗎？ - 是的
- This is a delicacy? - Yes.
顏色很不錯啊！
Such lovely colors!
- 是的 - 太美了
- Yes. - They are so pretty.
這是紅辣椒，你可以嘗嘗
This is paprika. You can try it.
可以嗎？
Can I?
「謝謝」怎麼說？
How to say "Thank you".
你喜歡嗎，弗洛倫斯？
Do you love it, Florence?
貝爾小姐
Miss Bell.
我沒走，希望能看見你
I stayed up, hoping I would see you.
我不是來打檯球的
I didn't come to play billiards.
那你來幹什麼？
Why did you come?
我是來看你撲克牌戲法的
I came for your card trick.
我明白了
I see.
撲克牌戲法
Card trick it is.
你走到這邊來
You have to come over here.
你看見了，牌是洗過的
As you can see, the deck is already shuffled.
紅色和黑色的牌是隨機擺放的
The red cards and the black cards are placed at random.
這個戲法很凶險的
This trick is fiendish.
從現在開始，我就不會再碰這些牌了
From this point on, I will not touch the cards.
你來做下面的事情
You'll do everything.
我？
Me?
我要給你下一個魔咒
I'm going to cast a spell over you.
在魔咒下，不看牌
And under this spell, without looking,
你就能決定牌是紅色的還是黑色的
you'll be able to determine if the card is red or if it is black.
不看牌？
Without looking at the cards?
那不可能
That's impossible.
根據機會率
According to the laws of probability.
在我的魔咒下...
Under my spell...
不存在規律
the laws do not exist.
你可以開始了
You may begin.
不要翻過來
Do not turn it over.
我沒有
I'm not.
是什麼顏色？
What color is it?
黑色
Black.
紅色
Red.
黑色
Black.
紅色
Red.
黑色，黑色
Black. Black.
紅色，紅色，紅色
Red. Red. Red.
瞧
Voila.
卡多根先生，當你把它們翻過來的時候
Mr. Cadogan, you did touch the cards again.
你又碰這些牌了
When you turned them over.
格特魯德，你非常聰明
Gertrude, you're very smart.
你是唯一注意到這個細節的人
You're the only one who's ever noticed that.
你剛才叫我「格特魯德」，亨利？
Did you just call me "Gertrude", Henry?
是的
Yes, I did.
你剛才叫我亨利？
And did you just call me Henry?
隔牆有耳
The walls have ears.
戲法是什麼原理？
How does the trick really work?
我不打算告訴你
I'm not going to tell you.
但是你已經很接近了
But you're very close.
是嗎？
Am I?
我喜歡這裡的鳥
I love the birds here.
我來這裡想看看這些鳥
I come here for the birds.
這裡是寂靜之塔
This is the Tower of Silence.
格特魯德，你確定要爬上去嗎？
Gertrude, you're sure you wish to climb all the way up?
是的，我確定
Yes, I'm sure.
是的
Yes.
這可能有骨頭
There may be bones.
也許有頭顱
Maybe skulls.
也許還有禿鷹
Maybe vultures.
我們會激怒禿鷹嗎？
What if we anger the vultures?
它們也許聽見我們的聲音飛走了
They've probably heard us and flown away.
就像我告訴你的
As I told you,
瑣羅亞斯德教教徒把屍體放在這裡留給禿鷹
this is what the Zoroastrians leave their dead to the vultures.
他們認為這樣很神聖
They considered them sacred.
你害怕嗎？
You're scared?
我不怕
I'm not afraid.
格特魯德 洛西恩 貝爾
Gertrude Lowthian Bell.
我想吻你
I wish to kiss you.
也許不應該在這裡做
Maybe we shouldn't do it here.
快跑
Run. Come on.
弗洛倫斯，別哭泣了
Florence, stop that moody brooding.
- 父親 - 弗蘭克
- Father... - Frank.
- 別總叫我 - 她是個孩子
- Don't Frank me. - She's a girl.
我吃飯的時候不允許哭泣
My dinner table is a no cry zone.
我很抱歉給你生了個女兒，很顯然你想要個男孩
I'm sorry I gave birth to a daughter. You wanted a boy, obviously.
當然不是了！
Absolutely not!
你只生了一個，我有些介意
You could've born me a dromedary, and I would have minded.
看，親愛的
Now look, darling.
眼淚也有好的一面
There is a good side about tears.
如果你把眼淚都哭出來，你的小便就會減少了
If you cry them out, you need to pee much less.
讓我們來抽根雪茄吧
Let's smoke a cigar together.
- 麵包 - 是的
- Bread. - Yeah.
一片麵包
A piece of bread.
一條麵包
A loaf of bread.
阿拉伯紅酒，一瓶紅酒
Sharab wine. A flask of wine.
還有...
And so...
你做的很好
You're doing so well.
- 是嗎？ - 是的
- I am? - Yes.
「一條麵包，在樹下，一瓶紅酒，一本詩集」
"A loaf of bread beneath the bough. A flask of wine, a book of verse.
「你在我旁邊在荒野裡唱歌」
"And Thou beside me singing in the wilderness.
「荒野現在是天堂」
"And wilderness is paradise enow."
還要
More.
看這句詩
Look at this verse.
「鳥兒有時間但很有限」
"The bird of time has but a little way.
「去飛翔」
"To fly."
- 偉大的亞歷山大  - 是的
- Alexander the Great. - Yeah.
有2200年歷史了
That's 2,200 years looking at you.
- 這個給我的？ - 不
- It is for me? - No.
給你一半
Only half.
有個銀匠把這個分成了兩半
I had a silversmith tie it in two.
所以一半給你，另一半是我的
So half is for you and half is for me.
不管你在世界什麼地方
Wherever you are in the world,
不管我在哪裡
and wherever I might be,
這個證明我們屬於對方
this is proof that we belong to each other.
如果我們中的一個死了，之後另一個人要保留完整的硬幣
And if one of us dies, then the other keeps the whole coin.
亨利
Henry.
格特魯德 洛西恩 貝爾
Gertrude Lowthian Bell,
你願意嫁給我嗎？
will you marry me?
我沒聽錯吧？
Did I hear you correctly?
是的，嫁給我，你願意嫁給我嗎？
Yes, marry me. Will you marry me ?
你不應該下跪嗎？
Shouldn't you get down on your knees?
哦，不
Oh, no.
我做錯了
I did it wrong.
- 是的 - 同意了？
- Yes. - Yes?
好的，你願意嫁給我嗎？
Alright, will you marry me?
我願意
I will.
亨利？
Henry?
你在幹什麼？
What are you doing?
你是怎麼繞過衛兵通過梯子來到這裡的？
How did you pass the security guards with a ladder?
我知道如何做生命中最重要的事情
I know how to do all the most important things in life.
但是你會掉下去的
But you could've fallen into your daddy.
這很重要，我解決了一個特別特殊的秘密
It was very important that I solve a particular mystery.
什麼秘密？
What mystery?
你看...
Well, you see...
我喜歡你的笑容
I love your smile.
但是很多男人墜入愛河都是因為女人的笑容
But many men in love with a woman's smile
犯了錯誤就娶了女孩兒
have made the mistake of marrying the whole girl.
這裡就有個女孩兒
Here's the whole girl.
我很奇怪，為什麼我父親還沒有回答我
I wonder why my father hasn't answered me.
別擔心，總是會有延遲的
Don't worry, there's always a delay
因為郵件在倫敦需要在外交部分類
because the mail needs to be sorted in the foreign office in London.
兩天前我發了電報
Two days ago I sent a telegram.
你發了電報？
You sent a telegram?
從大使館？
From the embassy?
- 那麼...所有人都知道我們的事情了？ - 不
- So... everyone knows about us? - No.
不是的，我只是說，「你回答我了嗎？」
No, I only said: "Have you sent an answer?"
我什麼都沒收到
And I've heard nothing.
什麼回答也沒有
Nothing from him.
我很擔心
I'm worried.
我能幫你什麼？
Can I help you?
急件，我沒有電報
From dispatch. I don't have a telegram.
但是我注意到郵遞員有給你的封信
But I noticed that the mailwoman had this letter for you.
我知道你在等
I knew you were waiting.
我在這聽你使喚
I'm always here for you.
我要...
I would...
- 我要...- 要怎樣？
- I would... - Would what?
我要把一切獻給像你這樣的女人
I would give my life for a woman like you.
我要回家，我要和我父親談談
I shall return home, I shall speak to my father.
愛是無辜的，別走
Love is lawless. Don't go.
他的證書沒什麼用
His credentials are not impressive.
我不管這些
I don't care.
你知道一個小外交官能掙多少錢啊？
Do you have any idea how little the junior diplomat earns?
我可以住帳篷的 - 一個帳篷！ - 和一個心愛的人
I could live in a tent - a tent! - with the man I love.
我能發現他什麼呢，你又有多少不知道的呢...
What I have found out about him and what you probably do not know...
我知道一切
I know everything.
你不知道這個男人是個賭徒
What you probably do not know is the man's a gambler.
他有很多的債務
He has accumulated significant debts.
你也有很多的債務啊
And you had an enormous debt.
當你開鋼廠的時候
When you started your steel mill. You did.
- 我的回答是不 - 為什麼？
- My answer remains no. - Why ?
我不同意這個...
I will not give my consent to this...
幼稚的想法
This childish plan.
夜鶯內心流出的血滴
The nightingale with the drops Of his heart's blood
滋養著紅玫瑰
Had nourished the red rose.
之後風來了
Then came the wind.
妒忌的心情，心煩意亂
And catching at the boughs in envious mood,
他的心中縈繞著大量的荊棘
a hundred thorns about his heart entwined.
這是來自德黑蘭的外交郵件
This just arrived by diplomatic pouch from Tehran.
上面說，在河旁邊的岩石上發現了
It says that the coin and the clothes of Mr. Henry Cadogan
亨利 卡多根的衣服和硬幣
were found neatly arranged on a rock by the river.
卡多根的屍體第二天也被發現
Cadogan's body was found the following day
在懸崖的下面
at the bottom of a cliff.
河的對岸
On the opposite side of the river.
大使館很遺憾的通知你，這是一個意外事故
The embassy regret to inform you about this tragic accident.
這不是意外事故
It was no accident.
這裡還有一個卡多根的留言
There's also a short note from Cadogan,
我猶豫是否給你
which I hesitate to give to you.
格特魯德，我要走了
Gertrude, I'll leave you now.
永恆的愛情在他自由的羽翼中
Eternal love doth keep In his complacent arms
大地，空氣，深淵
The earth, the air, the deep.
我眼睛的光芒，內心的收穫
Light of mine eyes and harvest of my heart
最後變成了永恆的記憶
And mine at last in changeless memory
啊！當你發現他就這樣匆匆離去
Ah! When he found it easy to depart
他給我留下來艱難的人生旅程
He left the harder pilgrimage to me
哦，啟動新的旅程
Oh Camel-driver Though the cordage start
務必幫助我鼓舞我的士氣
For God's sake Help me lift the fallen load
憐憫總是伴隨著我
And pity be my comrade of the road
我的臉上都是塵土，眼睛也濕潤了
My face is seamed with dust Mine eyes are wet
碧藍的天空下都是塵土和眼淚
Of dust and tears The turquoise firmament
沒有高興的徵兆，可是
Kneadeth the bricks for joy's abode. And yet,
我沒有氣餒，時間飛逝
I had not castled And the time is gone.
我該怎麼辦？
What shall I play?
白天和黑夜，日夜交替
Upon the chequered floor Of night and day
死亡贏得了遊戲
Death won the game.
三年後
我人生中第一次認識到我的本質
For the first time in my life I know who I am.
我的內心不屬於任何人，它只屬於沙漠
My heart belongs to no one now, but the desert.
- 幾年吧 - 幾年？
- For years. - Years ?
但是為什麼在戰爭中要去沙漠呢？
But why venturing out in the desert, in times of war?
你有沙漠的經驗嗎？
Have you ever experienced the desert?
這該怎麼辦？
What does that got to do with it?
我想知道的是，你為什麼來這裡？
What I would like to know is this: what brings you here?
你說，為什麼你離開倫敦更好？
Why did you leave England for good, as you say?
坦白講，我都不理解我自己
To be honest, I did not fully understood myself.
但是我很得意
But I did have my moment of epiphany.
貝爾小姐，恕我直言
Miss Bell, allow me to be candid.
聽起來很遺憾
This sounds pathetic.
你有什麼目的呢？
And what are your intentions?
我的目的是離開這裡
My intentions are to move out there
去做些考古的研究
and do some archaeological research.
- 去研究貝都因人 - 貝都因人？
- Study the Bedouins. - The Bedouins?
這樣不行
This is not going to happen.
我要提醒你，那裡是土耳其的管轄
May I remind you they're under Turkish administration.
你打算申請許可嗎？
Are you going to ask for their permit?
不，我也不需要你的許可
No, and I'm not going to ask for your permit either.
別忘了一件事
Do not forget one thing.
別忘了，我們要征服他們的帝國
Do not forget that soon, we intend to inherit their empire
我不想給我們付出的努力惹上麻煩
I do not want trouble for our ongoing efforts.
你不能引起和土耳其的對抗
You will not stir up confrontation with Turkey
因為貝都因人，他們長期不和
because of the Bedouins. They are feuding among themselves.
這很冒險，達不到目的還很危險
Now this little venture of yours is counterproductive and dangerous.
你無權利阻止我
You have no power to stop me.
你不能離開
You will not leave.
我要去
Yes, I will.
我已經去過那裡了，我要回去
I have already been out there and I'm going back.
祝好，先生們
Good day, gentlemen.
貝爾小姐，我會不惜一切代價
Ms. Bell, even if it costs me
讓土耳其知道你的計劃
to let the Turkish authorities know about your plans,
他們會阻止你的
they will intercept you.
這個愚蠢的計劃不會實現的！
This silly business of yours is not going to happen!
- 阿圖 - 是的，貝爾小姐
- Fattuh. - Yes, Ms. Bell.
你知道，我們會被捕嗎？
Do you know and the rest of the men know that we may all be arrested?
我有準備
I'm prepared.
為了這個？
Even for that?
阿圖總是有備而來
Fattuh is always prepared.
你們被捕了！
You are under arrest!
你們都被捕了！
All of you are under arrest!
中尉，有什麼我能幫忙的嗎？
Lieutenant, is there something I can help you with?
誰允許你們在沒有許可的情況下
Who allowed you to leave in the middle of the night,
半夜離開的？
without a permit by the authorities?
- 這裡是不是有誤會... - 我們有許可
- There must be some misunderstanding... - We do have a permit.
- 你是誰？ - 我是阿圖，我是貝爾小姐的隨從
- You, who are you? - I'm Fattuh. The servant of Ms. Bell.
格特魯德 貝爾小姐，我知道你是誰，你帶武器了嗎？
Ms. Gertrude Bell, I know who you are. Do you have any weapons?
不，我們沒有
No. We do not.
- 這份文檔是直接來自... - 這份文檔直接來自伊斯坦布爾
- This document comes directly... - It comes directly from Istanbul.
直接來自政府
Directly from the ministry.
貝爾小姐，我很抱歉
Ms. Bell, I'm so sorry.
我從我們安曼總部聽說...
I heard from our headquarters in Amman...
一個人一般不會被政府注意到的
A man probably just was not notified by your government.
都是官僚主義，都一樣的，甚至倫敦都這樣
The ways of bureaucracy are labyrinthal. It's always the same, even in London.
在我們的外交部，所以...
In our Foreign Office, so...
- 就這樣？ - 是的
- Is that so? - Yes. Yes.
謝謝，中尉
Thank you, Lieutenant.
你的馬看來需要喝水啊
Your horses look like they need some water.
你需要和我們待一會嗎？
Would you like to share a moment with us?
你哪裡拿到的許可？
Where did you get the permit?
我在安曼清真寺認識一個抄寫員
I know this scribe in the main mosque in Amman.
他可以偽造任何東西
He can forge anything for a good bakchich.
阿圖
Fattuh.
中尉
Lieutenant.
你是從鐵路那裡來的守衛部隊？
Did you come from the garrison at the railway?
是的，女士
Yes, lady.
那裡還有多少騎兵？
And how many cavalries are stationed there?
大約60人
About 60.
但是人數還在減少
But their numbers are dwindling.
四月的時候還有100人
We were 100 in April.
- 炮兵部隊呢？ - 解散了
- Artillery? - All gone.
我不應該和你說這些的
I should not tell you that.
我只是個旅行者和科學家
I'm just a traveler and a scientist.
所有人都知道土耳其帝國武力
Everyone knows that the forces of the Ottoman Empire
一直在擴展
are somewhat overstretched.
此外，這些都印在官方報紙上呢
Besides, it's all officially in the papers.
但是我的前哨部隊報紙上沒提起過
But my outpost is not in the papers.
中尉
Lieutenant.
我想給你們拍張照片
I would like to offer you a photograph.
你太客氣了，貝爾女士
You are very kind, lady Bell.
- 你和你的士兵，可以嗎？ - 是的，我很喜歡
- You and your men. Do you accept? - Yes, I'd like to.
因為我不想涉及軍事秘密
Because I do not wish to carry a military secret,
我不想給你們曝光
I'm going to give you the exposed negative.
- 你可以在安曼得到 - 謝謝
- You can have it developed in Aman. - Thank you.
站在中間
I would say right in the middle.
好的
Yes.
光線很好
The light is beautiful.
看這裡
Over here.
好極了
Superb.
親愛的日記
Dear diary,
我們到達了一個綠洲，貝都因人寓言中的某個地方
we have reached an oasis that is something from a Bedouin fable.
幽靜的沙漠，給了我孤獨人生一個安慰
The solitude of the desert gives me consolation in my own solitude.
阿圖問我為什麼總是要兩杯茶
Fattuh asked me why I always request two glasses of tea.
我能告訴他
Should I tell him
這是給我心中的愛人的嗎？
this is for the man who lives in my heart?
一天又一天，我們繼續前進
Day in, day out. We keep moving ahead.
總是在依照慣例紮營
And setting up camp is the same familiar routine.
但是我們進入沙漠越深
But the deeper we immerse ourselves into the desert
所有事情就像是夢一樣
The more everything seems like a dream.
有時候，我們去的地方幾乎無法通過
Some days we move across terrain that is almost impassable.
就像是很堅硬的食鹽，就像是破碎的瓷器
Like the hard crust of salt, like shards of broken porcelain.
我常常不看地圖，只是憑我的好奇心指引我前進
Often I don't follow any map, but merely go where my curiosity leads me.
在死海東部，我在瓦迪 穆吉發現了秘密的峽谷
East of the Dead Sea I explored the hidden gorge of Wadi Mujib.
我從沒想過在沙漠也能發現如此新鮮的水源
I never expected to find water so fresh in the desert.
找到越多神秘的地方
The deeper I penetrate this mysterious labyrinth
我就越發瞭解我自己
The more I become known to myself
在峽谷的盡頭，阿圖發現了一件神奇的東西
Near the end of the gorge, Fattuh found something curious.
應該是新石器時代的矛
It turned out to be a Neolithic spear.
至少有1萬年歷史了
At least 10,000 years old.
我猜在遠古時代
I speculated that in prehistoric times,
那裡一定有戰爭
there must have been war here.
這裡一定是個很不錯的防守要地
And that this must have been a very defensible place.
但是阿圖說，「這不可能」
But Fattuh said: "This cannot be."
在早期，世界是個天堂
At such an early time, the world was paradise.
如果我們的一生正直的話，天堂就在召喚我們
And paradise is meant to come upon us again if we leave a righteous life.
這是預言家說的
As foretold by the Prophet.
天堂沒有時間，沒有年齡，沒有住所
Paradise has no time, no age, no dwelling place.
在等待著我們
It awaits us.
這讓我渴望深入去考古
This made me eager to go deeper into archeology.
離峽谷不遠是英國發掘的佩特拉古跡
Not far from the gorge is the British excavation site of Petra.
這是艱難的一天，因為一直在下雨
It was a hard day's travel because of the arrival of early rain.
好極了
Greetings.
歡迎，貝爾小姐！
Welcome, Ms. Bell!
歡迎來到我們的家！
Welcome to our home!
我是坎貝爾 湯普森，這是我的同事，T.E 羅倫斯
I'm Campbell Thompson. This is my colleague, T.E. Lawrence.
T.E 代表什麼？
And what does "T.E." stand for?
T.E 代表愛德華 托馬斯
T.E. stands for Edward Thomas.
我不喜歡那兩個名字，太討厭了
I despise both names. They're an abomination.
- 就叫我勞倫斯吧 - 好的，勞倫斯
- Please just call me Lawrence. - Will do, Lawrence.
我們知道你要來
We knew you were coming.
真的嗎？ 我們沒送消息來啊
Really? We didn't send messengers.
星星在夜裡看見了你
A meeting of the stars saw you at night,
白天，沙子留下了你的腳印
and during the day, the sand down your footsteps.
抱歉，他總是這樣
Sorry, he's always like this.
像你這樣的學生在這裡幹什麼，勞倫斯？
What's a school boy like you doing here, Lawrence?
這個特殊的學生有考古的博士學位
This particular school boy has a PhD in archeology.
湯普森...
Thompson...
我有中世紀陶瓷博士學位
I have a PhD in medieval pottery shards.
他就像一個老傢伙一樣，一直跟隨著我
It follows me around like the wafting of an old pinster's fart.
我多久才能擺脫他啊！
How I long to be rid of it!
可以嗎？
Shall we?
這地方太糟糕了
This place is a dump.
所有東西都被盜墓者偷走了
Everything has been moved by grave robbers.
一次又一次的
Over and over again.
我們在這裡不知所措
We're simply stuck here.
勞倫斯夢想財寶，大量的金子
Lawrence dreams of great treasures, hoards of gold.
至少...
At least...
萬能的金子，給了我們巴比倫居民的泥瓦片的圖書館
God Almighty, give us a library of Babylonian clay tablet
就像德國人發掘美索不達米亞那樣
the likes that the Germans have excavated in Mesopotamia.
我們的挖掘方法不適合他們
Our excavation methods are no match for theirs.
這是事實，格特魯德，親愛的
This is true, Gertrude, darling.
「親愛的」
"Darling".
你知道，我在這裡季這種腰帶犯了個大錯
You know, I made a big mistake wearing this belt here.
這種腰帶只有單身漢才季
That kind of belt is only worn by bachelors.
然後呢？
And...?
然後...本地的挖掘工人
And... the local excavation workers
就試圖給我找個老婆
have been trying to find me a wife.
想像一下，給我找老婆，太可怕了！
Imagine. A wife for me. How horrible!
但是他們聽說你要來
But they heard of your arrival
謠言四起，說你是我
and instant rumor spread that you're my bride,
從英國來的新娘
sent from England.
我覺得適合你的人還沒出生呢
I'm not sure the right man for you had been born yet.
對於我來講，土耳其帝國撐不了多久了
To me, the Ottoman Empire can't last much longer
就像羅馬帝國一樣，在垮台前迅速消失
and it looks like the Roman Empire shall disappear before its collapse.
你覺得會發生什麼？
What do you think's gonna happen?
混亂
Chaos.
混亂和戰爭
Chaos and war.
你覺得大英帝國能接管嗎
Do you think the British Empire will take over
- 填補上管理的空缺？  - 不，我不敢苟同
- and  fill the void of power? - No, I beg to differ.
我相信一個阿拉伯民族會出現
I believe one of the Arabs'spiritual nations will emerge.
他們才是未來
They are the future.
也許，但是...
Perhaps, but...
任何一個重大的變化可能需要一個世紀的時間
Any meaningful change may take centuries to launch.
- 我們有生之年就能看見... - 十足的政治
- It will happen in our lifetime... - Enough politics.
或者幾十年
Or in a few decades.
我們是考古學家
We are archaeologists.
至今，我還是個旅行者
So far, I am only a traveler.
那麼，對於旅行者
Well then, to the travelers.
對於那些發掘地下神秘寶藏的人
And to those who dig up mysteries from under the surface.
很抱歉，我們沒有杯子
I'm sorry, we have no glasses.
你知道嗎，格特魯德？
You know what, Gertrude?
不管別人怎麼說
Regardless of what anyone says,
在溫和耀眼的篝火前
under the benign, soft glove of campfire
手握蘇格蘭酒
with good scotch in your fist,
你會是個很好的新娘
you'd make an terrific bride.
格特魯德！
Gertie!
你吃早飯了嗎？
You had breakfast yet?
喝醉了
Got a hangover.
我頭疼，就像羅馬帝國那麼大
I have a Roman Empire size headache.
很遺憾我們沒有羅馬式的激情
What a shame we do not have Rome set on fire
羅馬暴君尼祿說起我們經歷。我在火災中呻吟
and Nero singing to us live. I've been moaning the conflagration.
他自己心情不好，就放火
He himself started the fire under the right mood.
- 那些是不錯的日子 - 勞倫斯，別說了
- Those were the good days. - Lawrence, keep it down.
格特魯德
Gertie.
你不能離開
You can't leave.
當地的女人正試圖給我找個老婆呢
The local women might try to find me a wife.
你想讓我當眾吻你嗎？
Do you want me to kiss you in front of everyone?
絕對需要
Absolutely.
我的吻...
My kiss...
我的吻可以釋放你
My kiss shall liberate you.
好極了
Wonderful!
格特魯德...
Gertie...
你能，別嫁給我嗎？
would you, please, not marry me?
當然
Absolutely.
三個月後
大馬士革英國領事辦公室
請進吧
Please, do come in.
貝爾小姐，這是領事
Ms. Bell, the consul.
貝爾小姐...歡迎！
Ms. Bell... welcome!
歡迎回來！
Welcome back!
在我們談話之前，請讓我恭喜你
Before we talk business, allow me to congratulate you
通過了土耳其當局的檢查
on your feat of alluding the Turkish authorities.
我有許可，你是否知道我的意思
Well, I had a permit, if you know what I mean.
你怎麼弄到的？
How did you forge it?
不是我，是清真寺偉大的抄寫員
It wasn't me, it was a scribe from the Great Mosque.
一個高手
One of the finest.
是的，是我的隨從聯繫的
Yes, it was my servant who contacted him.
我確信，如果你需要這個文件，我們可以安排的
I'm sure if you ever needed a document, we could arrange.
大英帝國沒必要耍這等小把戲
The British Empire has no need for such petty tricks.
不
No.
除非要印刷百萬的德國馬克假幣
Except for printing millions of counterfeit Deutschmarks
土耳其想消弱他們的經濟的話
and Turkish piastres, in order to undermine their economies.
請坐
Please, take a seat.
那麼...
Well...
我來這裡是要通知你我計劃去德魯士旅行
I'm here to inform you of my plans to travel to Jabal al-Druze.
你不是認真的吧
You can't be serious.
是的，很嚴肅的
Yes, I most certainly am.
這十年來沒有人去過德魯士
No one has traveled to the Druze in decades.
那是時間問題
So it's about time.
沒有英國士兵會陪你去的，貝爾小姐
No British soldier will accompany you, Ms. Bell.
那意味著對德魯士人的挑釁
It'd mean a provocation for the Druze people.
- 我自己做為一個士兵... - 陸軍上校...
- I myself as a soldier... - Major...
韋爾奇皇家火槍隊的陸軍上校
Major of the Royal Welch Fusiliers.
貝爾小姐，我們似乎已經瞭解對方了
Ms. Bell, we seem to know quite a lot about each other already.
陸軍上校...
Major...
我來是問問你是否準備好了去做一個志願者
I'm here to ask you for what you're already so graciously volunteering.
即使你幾個月也沒看到我的來信
Even if you do not hear from me for several months
沒有注意我，也不回復我
pay no attention and send no one.
- 德魯士人會認為你是個間諜 - 是的，也許我就是
- The Druze will take you for a spy. - Yeah, or maybe I am.
也許我是個間諜，但是我是我自己的間諜
Maybe I am a spy, but I am a spy for no one.
是我自己的
No one but myself.
我是領事的妻子
I am the consul's wife.
- 是的 - 別太拘束，親愛的
- Yes. - Don't be so formal, dear.
貝爾小姐，這是朱迪斯
Ms. Bell, this is Judith. Welcome.
我給你帶來了禮物
I brought you a present.
你們一人一個
One for each of you.
你太客氣了
This is very kind.
我在露天市場發現的
It's just something I found in a souk.
- 我該如何是好呢？ - 太漂亮了
- What do I do with it? - That's beautiful.
親愛的，可以在廚房用來切洋蔥
My love, use them in the kitchen for your onions.
來吧
Come.
但是德魯士人很獨立
But the Druze are fiercely independent.
反對一切東西，反對土耳其
And more than anything, anti-Turkish.
事實上，他們是唯一擊敗土耳其的人
In fact, they're the only people ever to have defeated the Turks.
這到另人很感興趣
Ans this is what makes them so interesting.
另外，他們的宗教信仰有基督教徒，諾斯替教徒，新教
Besides, their faith incorporates Christian, Gnostic, Neoplatonic,
包含了整個的伊斯蘭信仰
which overlay their Islamic beliefs.
別再談這些柏拉圖了
Please, let's not talk about Plato.
你還想要些燕麥粉嗎？
Would you like some more of the couscous?
親愛的，我們不是在討論柏拉圖
We're not talking about Plato, my love.
我們在討論的是一個很大的危險，貝爾小姐的信仰
We're talking about a very grave danger: Ms. Bell's faith.
這是值得的
It will be worthwhile.
要當心
Be careful.
德魯士人不按遊戲規則辦事
The Druze do not play the game as it should be played.
他們外出搞屠殺，趕盡殺絕
They go out to slay, and they spare no one.
他們的槍裡裝滿了火藥
While they have enough dry powder in their flasks,
隨時準備扣動扳機
and strenghth to pull the trigger,
他們殺掉所遇到的所有男人，女人和小孩兒
they kill every man, woman and child they encounter.
好可怕啊！
How awful!
- 什麼？  - 我要你拿著這些
- What? - I want you to have them.
不...
No...
不，太多了
No, it's too much.
親愛的...
Dear...
你不是說過好幾次，不再拿出這些手槍了嗎？
Have you no said on several occasions you would never give these pistols away?
那麼...
Well...
現在，它們要消失了
Now they are, given away.
貝爾小姐，送給你了
Ms. Bell, for you.
給我了？
For me?
我們正穿越貝都因人廣闊的地域
We are traveling across the vast expanse of Bedouin lands.
我密切關注著這裡複雜的
And my eyes are opening to the complexity
部族關係
of tribal relations here.
阿圖是我所有一切的指導老師
Fattuh has been my gracious teacher in all of this.
他說，衝突主要發生在德魯士人和貝尼 莎哈人之間
He says the most volatile conflict is between the Druze and the Beni Sakhr.
我擔心的是奧馬爾，貝爾小姐
My worry is Omar, Ms. Bell.
是的，我早上發現他是貝尼 莎哈人
Yes, I only found out this morning that he was Beni Sakhr.
我們應該留下他嗎？
Should we leave him behind?
德魯士人和貝尼 莎哈人之間都是毫不留情的
There's no mercy between Druze and Beni Sakhr.
如果他們兩者相遇，只有一個能活下來
If two of them meet, only one survives.
貝爾小姐！
Ms. Bell!
是的
Yes.
我覺得，德魯士人能通過口音發現奧馬爾
I realized that the Druze would recognize Omar as a Beni Sakhr
是貝尼 莎哈人
by his accent.
我怎麼沒想到啊
I did not think about that.
我們該怎麼辦？
What do we do?
問問奧馬爾
Ask Omar.
奧馬爾，我要早點把你送回去嗎？
Omar, should I send you back before it's too late?
奧馬爾突然變成了啞巴
Omar suddenly became a deaf-mute.
什麼時候？
When?
一小時之前
An hour ago.
你們是我的犯人了，你們會死的！
You are my prisoners, you'll die!
- 你們所有人！ - 如果我死了...
- All of you! - If I die...
要死也要死在你們酋長的手裡
it should be at the hands of your sheikh.
你們的酋長在哪兒？- 帶我去見他
Where's your sheikh? Take me to him.
- 貝爾小姐，你受傷了！ - 沒事
- Ms. Bell, you're wounded! - Nothing.
沒事，帶我去見酋長！
Nothing. Give me your sheikh now!
現在！
Now!
女人要通過女人的入口進入
A woman passes through the entrance at the women's side.
拿我當男人看待吧
This woman is joining the men.
請坐
Sit down.
請坐，女人
Sit down, woman.
請坐
Please.
你怎麼敢來這裡？
Who are you to dare come here?
我是格特魯德 貝爾
I'm Gertrude Bell.
我是大英帝國的科學家
And I am a subject of the British Empire.
感謝主，你不是德國人
Thank the Almighty that you're not German.
請坐吧
Have a seat, please.
我每天都感謝他，我不是的
I thank him every day that I am not.
- 你是間諜嗎？ - 不
- Are you a spy? - No.
我是個作家
I'm a writer.
我描寫美麗的大陸和民族
I write about the beauty of the land and its people.
那麼你是個詩人
So, you're a poet.
可以說是的，但是我不是只描述...
In a way, but in fact, I do not describe...
我所見到的...
what I see...
我只描述它的美麗
I just name its beauty.
很多脈絡中的...
Much in the vein of the...
羅馬詩人維吉爾
Roman poet Virgil.
他是一個伊尼德
He's an aeneid.
是的
Yes.
我很抱歉，但是德魯士的酋長怎麼知道維吉爾的呢？
I'm so sorry, but how does the sheikh of the Druze know about Virgil?
我常旅行...隱姓埋名
I have traveled... incognito.
我去過大馬士革
I've been to Damascus.
去過貝魯特
To Beirut.
去過巴黎
To Paris.
法國的愛麗捨是世界上最美的大道
Les Champs-Elyss, la plus belle avenue du monde.
波德萊爾...
Baudelaire...
邪惡之花
Et ses "Fleurs du mal". Rimbaud.
你是對的，這個詩人從不描述任何事情
You're right, this poet never describes anything.
他只描述宗教的榮耀
He just names the glory of the trees,
蜂巢...
the beehives...
國民的生活
and the life in the country.
他喜歡我們詩文
He's like our poets.
是的
This is true.
我可以叫我的隨從進來嗎？
May I ask in one of my trusted men?
請吧
Please do.
阿圖...
Fattuh...
你能把我的木箱子拿來嗎？
would you fetch me my wooden case?
貝爾小姐...
Ms. Bell...
我希望我的人沒有傷害到你
I hope my men didn't hurt you.
他們做了，但是只是個小傷，這個我們叫做恩賜
They did, but it is a small wound. It is what we call grace.
請原諒他們
Forgive them.
他們不懂事理
They know no better.
對不起
I'm sorry.
我想給你一個禮物
I want like to give you a gift.
這是對於我很珍貴的，有人送給我的
It is something very precious to me and it was given to me. And now,
現在送給你了
now, it is yours.
很精緻啊！
Exquisite!
作為客人留下來
Stay as my guest.
你將得到我們熱情的款待
You are under the protection of our hospitality.
很高興你回來了
Good to have you back.
受了點小傷...但是還活著
A noble bow wound... but alive.
沒事的
Please, it's nothing. Nothing.
但是，我得承認一件事情
But I have to admit something.
- 我把手槍送人了 - 他們不是我的，是你的
- I gave away your pistols - They were not mine, but yours.
但是，是你送給我的
But you gave them to me.
最終，變得有用了，達到目的了
Finally, it became useful. It was the purpose.
- 我很抱歉 - 貝爾小姐
- I'm sorry. - Ms. Bell,
請保持安靜？最後，有些事發生了
will you please keep quiet? Finally, someting happened.
子彈
Bullets.
現在我有個新的計劃，我要去哈里
Now I have a new plan, I want to go to Hayri.
但是，這是阿拉伯沙漠的中部，那可是禁區啊
But it is the middle of the Arabian desert. It's the forbidden zone.
我們只有一些來自十九世紀五十年代年旅行者的報告
We have only a few reports from some travelers in the 1950's.
為什麼是哈里？
Why for God's sake Hayri?
因為這是阿拉伯世界的神秘中心
Because it is the secret epicenter of the Arab world
我要見見埃米爾 莫哈默德
and I want to meet the emir Ibn Rashid.
他很重要，他是阿拉伯的領袖
He is important He is the leader of Arabia.
- 誰和你一起去？ - 阿圖
- Who would be with you? - Fattuh.
還有我的人
And my men.
怎麼了？ 我信任他們
What? I trust them.
你到的太早了
You arrived too early.
- 想讓我晚點回去？ - 不
- Want me to come back later? - No.
不，不
No, no, no.
這是幹什麼？
What's going on?
- 這是給你的種馬  - 給我的？
- This stallion is for you. - For me ?
你在阿拉伯需要最好的馬
You'll need the best horse in Arabia.
但是你在畫畫！我從沒見過這樣的
But you're painting it! I've never seen anything like it.
那麼...
Well...
- 那麼什麼？- 我必須承認
- Well, what? - I have to make a confession.
我為你偷的馬！
I stole him for you!
你為我偷的馬？
You stole this horse for me?
看看它的本事
See what he can do.
太棒了！
Bravo!
太棒了，撒拉丁
Bravo, Salhadin.
太棒了
Bravo.
我其實不是偷的，算是徵用吧
I didn't exactly steal him, it was more an act of expropriation.
- 在哪兒？ 從誰那裡？ - 從土耳其
-  Where? From who? - From the Turkish authorities.
可以說，從敵人那裡
From the enemy, so to speak.
怎麼弄的？
How?
我做了兩件事情
Well, there were  two things I did.
我付錢給當地的一個報社編輯
I paid off an editor of a local newspaper
寫一篇關於馬會傳播疾病的文章
to write about a disease spreading among the horses.
之後我弄了一個假的獸醫證
Then I took on a false credentials as a vet,
我直接去了土耳其的守衛部隊，我給馬做檢查
I went straight to the Turkish garrison, I inspected the horses
這匹種馬就在那裡，需要立即被轉移
and this here stallion here had to be removed immediately.
我就直接把它拉回來做「隔離」
And I put him straight into quarantine.
那麼，閣下，英國領事
So, His Excellency, the British consul
- 理查德 道蒂-懷利... - 我為你偷了馬
- Richard Doughty-Wylie... - I've stolen a horse for you.
貝爾小姐
Ms. Bell.
- 我叫你來，我... - 沒有人能叫我來
- I have summoned you and I... - No one summons me.
我是...邀請你來
I have... invited you.
聽起來好多了
That sounds vaguely better.
讓我們直入主題，好嗎？
Yes. Let's get straight to the point, shall we?
你勇於冒險，我並不傾向於這樣做
You ventured out, and I felt not inclined to support this.
說的委婉些
To put it mildly.
隨著第一次世界大戰的深入
With the size and momentum of the Great War that is gaining,
如果你將你的好奇的事情做的更系統些的話
it'd be of considerable value for our country
這會對國家相當有價值的
if you could make your curiosity more... systematic.
什麼意思？
Meaning what?
你將是我們情報機構
You would be our only spy
在廣闊區域裡唯一的間諜
in a vast area we have little intelligence about.
總之...不
In short... no.
- 直接拒絕- 是的，直接拒絕
- A blunt no. - Correct. A blunt no.
我不為任何人工作
I operate for no one.
那麼是什麼吸引你去貝都因的呢？
What is it then that attracts you to the Bedouin out there?
這是你和你的世界無法理解的
It is something that you and your world would never understand.
這是他們的自由
It's their freedom.
這是他們的尊嚴
It's their dignity.
這是他們生命的詩歌
It's their poetry of life.
祝你過得愉快
Have a good day.
懷利先生！
Mr. Wylie!
理查德，請叫我理查德
Richard. Please say Richard.
理查德...
Richard...
我還沒準備好
I'm not ready.
我再不能...
I would never be with...
你再不會怎樣？
You would never what?
我不能再和其他人交往
I would never be with a man again.
因為...
Because...
我失去了一個男人
I lost a man.
- 失去？  - 是的
- Lost? - Yes.
我是一個寡婦
I'm a widow.
寡婦？
A widow?
是的！不，不...
Yes! No, no...
有點...
Sort of.
- 我太傻了 - 不，這是...
- What a clumsy fool I've been. - No, it's...
請原諒我
Will you forgive me?
當然
Of course.
好吧...
Well...
我們還需要什麼？
What else do we need?
奎寧，解藥和蠍子
Quinine, and antidote against scorpions.
蠍子，不，我們得小心
Scorpions, no. We'll be watchful.
貝都因人被蟄傷過，不是嗎？
No Bedouin has ever been stung, am I right?
是的，夫人，聽你的
Yes, ma'am. As you wish.
這個市場什麼都有
This market has everything we need.
蚊帳，折疊床，浴缸
Mosquito net, a folding bed, a bathtub.
我們需要這個
We need this.
夫人的眼光不錯
The lady has a good eye.
我保證他們是最好的
I assure you they are the best.
- 我要懺悔 - 懺悔？
- I have confession to make. - A confession?
是的
Yes.
那麼好的一匹馬
As wonderful as the horse was,
不應該進入沙漠的
it'd never have made it in the dunes of the desert.
你做了什麼？
What did you do?
我把它賣了，阿圖在市場了做了交易
I traded it. Fattuh traded it in the market place.
換來了4只非常不錯的駱駝，在那兒呢
For four of the very best dromedaries. There they are.
我很抱歉
I'm sorry.
格特魯德，別現在就走
Gertrude, don't leave. Not now.
理查德，我別無選擇
Richard, I have no choice.
我內心還沒準備好
My heart is not ready.
我能感覺到
I can feel that.
- 再多待幾個星期 - 不，已經12月底了
- Stay for just a few more weeks. - No, it's late December.
很快，就去不成沙漠了
Very soon, the dessert won't be possible.
- 我很喜歡你 - 請別這樣說
- I'm longing for you. - Please do not say that.
別說這些事情了
Do not say these things.
- 沒有你我會很孤獨的 - 你有妻子啊
- It'll all be lonely without you. - You have a wife.
婚姻的不幸福，讓我有著無法忍受的孤獨
It is the most unbearable loneliness to be married unhappily.
這樣是沒有結果的，理查德
This comes at me from nowhere, Richard.
另外，我不可能和你結合，你是個已婚男士
Besides, I could never fully be yours. You're a married man.
我會安排好一切的
I'll settle everything.
你會給我寫信嗎？
Will you write to me?
每到沙漠的郵局，我都會給你寫信的
I'll write you from every post office in the desert.
我會給你留一本日記
I'll keep a diary for you.
風吹來了...
The wind...
吹來什麼？
What?
風吹來了沙子，吹來了沙塵暴
The wind is coming with sand.
1915年元旦
夫人你能教我怎麼做嗎？
Can the lady show me how to do it?
煮雞蛋？
To cook an egg?
沙漠不認識雞蛋，沙漠也不認識母雞
The desert knows no eggs. The desert knows no hens.
你煮大約5分鐘
You boil it for 5 minutes.
沙漠沒有時間的概念
The desert knows no minutes.
一個禱告那麼長的時間
The length of a prayer.
我有了個禮物
You have a present.
理查德...
Richard...
我試著不去想你
I'm trying to keep you out of my thoughts,
但是很奇怪
but it's strange.
在沙漠每走一步我都在想著你
You are on my mind in every step of the desert.
我的廚師沒有時間的觀念
My cook does not have a notion of time.
他都不會煮雞蛋
He's never boiled an egg.
可以說我已經落後了，沒有按時到達
Already I've dropped back in the desert as if it were my own place.
寂寞和孤獨縈繞著我，像是個阻擋我的面紗一樣
Silence and solitude fowling around me like an impenetrable veil.
比在城裡睡的深沉
Sleep more profound than civilization can thrive.
然後又是無際的沙漠
And then the roadless desert.
繼續前進
Again.
部落戰爭前，這裡還很有生機
Before the tribal wars, this place was alive.
現在，這裡只剩下幽靈了
Now there are only ghosts here.
這是什麼？
What is this?
這怎麼可能？
How is this possible?
從領事那裡來的信？
Is it from the consul?
領事的信必須夜以繼日不停的被送出
The consul's messenger must have been riding day and night.
我們今晚在這裡過夜
We shall stay here tonight.
我親愛的
My beloved,
沙漠有你，我的心也和你在一起
the desert has you and my heart is with you.
如果在一個美好的夜晚我能自由的話
If I was free and a very perfect night,
我會帶上你並且吻你
it's be more fitting to take you and kiss you.
上帝似乎給了我們結合的機會
God seems to have joined us for some divine moment.
啊，太高興了！
Ah, the ecstasy!
我們會再次見面的
We might reach it again,
在下一個前哨站
on an outpost of time.
我無法入睡...我無法入睡
I can't sleep... I can't sleep.
已經是早上了
It is one in the morning.
你和我之間還有少許的安寧
You and you and you are between me and any rest.
你喚醒了我的生命
You once called me life.
火焰，焰火，我燃燒殆盡
And fire. I flame and I'm consumed.
有句話我一直想說，那就是...
There is a voice in me I try to chase away. It says...
「在我有生之年，說出來，帶我走吧」
"Before all other world, claim me and take me."
可是...
And yet...
理查德...
Richard...
我覺得世界上所有人都和我一樣高興了
I doubt there is anyone in the world so happy as I am now.
你在沙漠中接受洗禮
You were baptised in the desert
這裡沒有你的救世主
and there is no another salvation for you.
當我們前進的時候，我感覺
When we are on the move, I feel
所有事情都過去了
everything is behind us.
唯有我的影子一直跟著我
Only our shadows follow.
這讓我們想起
As if to remind us
我們過去的生活
of our past lives.
你很勇敢，像貝都因人一樣
The lady is bold, as bold as any Bedouin man.
- 你的目的地是哈里？  - 是的
- Is your destination Hayri? - It is.
我想見見本 拉什德
I want to meet bin Rashid.
我們可以好好說說本 拉什德
We have to talk a lot about bin Rashid.
他是個很強大的敵人
It has powerful enemies.
沙特阿拉伯？
Ibn Saud?
還有其他的
Yes, and many others.
- 你在哈里見不到他的 - 他在哪兒？
- You will not find him in Hayri. - Where is he ?
他在南部打仗呢
He's at war in the South.
我以為已經和平了
I thought he was at peace.
不再是了。在哈里要特別小心，那裡還有各種謀殺
Not any longer. Beware of Hayri. There is a lot of murdering going on.
給我的？ - 是的
- For me? - Yes.
你這樣熱情的款待我
You've shown me such gratious hospitality.
你還給我講述了精彩的沙漠故事
And you have entertained me with wonderful desert stories.
每一個貝都因人都擅長講故事
Every Bedouin is a storyteller.
但是你還給我了很多關於哈里部落的信息
But you have also given insight into the tribes and the tribes of Hayri.
為了這個...我要好好感謝你
And for that... I want to thank you.
我想把這個送給你
I would like to give you these.
這是我的望遠鏡
These are my binoculars.
我現在可以看的很清楚了，所以我不再需要這個了
I can see clearly now, so I do not need him.
這是給你的禮物
These are a gift.
我將成為一個富有的旅行者
I've become a desert traveler who is very rich.
謝謝
Thank you.
我的嚮導，哈米德，會護送你們的
And my guide, Ahmed, will be your escort.
你一路上不會有事的
No harm will be done to you on your way.
但是到了哈里，可能就出不來了
But once in Hayri, no one gets out.
但憑天意，我很想再見到你...活著的
Inshallah. We want to see you again... alive.
但憑天意
Inshallah.
你可以看得非常遠
You can see very far.
奴隸，我不知道準確的含義
Slaves, I don't know exactly what this means.
但是，這是一種侮辱，我確定
But it's an insult, I'm sure.
只有女人可以
Only the woman.
男人留下來
Men will stay behind.
只有女人可以進去
Only the woman is invited here.
我是易卜拉欣
My name is Ibrahim.
我是法蒂瑪，埃米爾的姨媽
I am Fatima, the aunt of the emir.
她是突卡婭，她會接待你們的
This is Turkia, who will entertain you.
歡迎來到哈里
Welcome to Hayri.
你一定是沙漠女王
You must be the Lady of the desert.
傳聞比你的駱駝來的快啊
Rumor has been faster than your camels.
我是格特魯德 貝爾
I'm Gertrude Bell.
誰帶你來的？
Who has sent you?
沒有人
No one.
不，我自己來的
No, I'm here on my own.
你自己？
On your own?
我很通情達理
I know the world.
我從伊斯坦布爾來
I come from Istanbul.
蘇丹把我作為禮物送給了埃米爾 拉什德
The Sultan has sent me as a gift to Emir Rashid.
你有什麼計劃？
What are your plans?
我想見見埃米爾 拉什德
I would like to meet Emir Rashid.
埃米爾 拉什德被趕出哈里了
Emir Rashid has been driven off Hayri.
他的女人跟隨著他
His women followed him.
還有他的部落成員
And all tribe's men.
但是他卻把我留下了
But he left me behind.
- 他是埃米爾的客人？ - 是的
- He was a guest of the Emir? - Yes.
埃米爾 胡裡德，六年前
The Emir Harrud, six years ago.
發生什麼事情了？
What happened?
這個皇宮充滿了陰謀
This palace is full of conspiracies.
到處是暗殺
Full of murder.
埃米爾怎麼樣了？
What happened to the Emir?
他被謀殺了
He was assassinated.
他的繼承人也被謀殺了，之後的繼承人也被謀殺了
And his successor was murdered. And his successor as well.
所有人，在這幾年時間裡
All of them, a few years.
大臣也被殺了
The Eunuchs were killed with them
所有的女人都在男人之間被轉來轉去
and the entire harem was passed from man to man to man.
現在誰統治帝國呢？
Who is the ruling Emir now?
他的家族裡都沒什麼人了
There was hardly anyone left in his family.
他也很年輕
So, he's young.
他在北方打仗
He's raiding in the North.
法蒂瑪，他的姨媽
Fatima, his aunt,
是真正的統治者，她是真正的皇帝
is the true ruler. She is the real Emir.
太美了
It's beautiful.
我在這裡作為犯人被關了三個星期了
I have been a prisoner here for three weeks now.
你不是個犯人
You are not a prisoner.
你的人也被招待的很好
Your men are taken care well.
你只需待在這裡等待埃米爾的決定
You are only required to stay until the Emir decides.
決定什麼？
Decides what?
是否你待在這裡比較好
If it would be good to have you here.
為了什麼？
For what?
我希望你能留下來，做為埃米爾的妻子
My wish is to keep you here, in the harem of the Emir.
他會很高興的
He would be delighted.
法蒂瑪...
Fatima...
那不是我的願望
That is not my wish.
他什麼時候回來？
When does he get back?
你知道嗎？
Do you know?
我很高興歡迎我的客人
I am delighted to greet my guest.
他的意思是：「我很高興歡迎他的妻子」
He means: "I am delighted to greet his wife
「來到我的後宮」
"into my harem."
是的，我的妻子
Yes, my wife.
埃米爾...
Emir...
很榮幸見到你
It is an honor to meet you.
可是，我已經結婚了
However, I am already married.
和一個英國領事
I am a member of the British Consul.
這會給一個男人和他的國家帶來麻煩的
And this will cause a problem both for a man and his country.
我已經說過了
I was told otherwise.
「沒有人能碰一個已婚女人」
"No man ever touches a married woman",
預言家告訴我們，要和平相處
the Prophet, peace be upon him, has taught us.
親愛的理查德，我看到的事情已經很明確了
Dear Richard, it's clear from what I've seen
在哈里，莫哈默德的國家的確正在走向滅亡
that the house of Rashid is moving towards its demise.
現在阿拉伯半島卻發展迅速
It now appears that Ibn Fold'star is in the ascendant.
阿拉伯半島的未來就取決於他
And the future of Central Arabia lies with him,
並不是哈里人
not the people of Hayri.
我應該把這些告訴英國阿拉伯管理局
I should communicate this to the British Arab Bureau.
在我探索世界的這些年裡
The explorations that I have undertaken these past years,
部落和部落居民的生活，還有他們的政府
the terrains and its people of tribal life and governments,
展示出了一副美好的畫卷，只有我才能描繪出來
have culminated in a unique picture, one that only I can paint.
對於我自己，我感覺經過多年的準備
As for myself, I sense that long years of preparation,
準備什麼我也說不好，但已經接近尾聲了
preparation for what I do not know, have ended.
一個新的命運
And a new destiny
向我駛來
is infolding before me.
我只需要回到你的身邊
I have only now to return to you.
讓我們找個安靜的地方
Let's find somewhere quiet.
我閱讀了你的日記
I've read your diary.
這是給你寫的
It was meant for you.
世界在改變
The world is changing.
當我在沙漠裡的時候，戰爭已經發展為世界大戰
While I was in the desert, the war turned into a World Wide War
我都沒注意到
and I didn't even notice.
所有的歐洲國家
All of Europe now.
俄國，日本...
Russia, Japan...
美國也加入了
And America now. They will have it too.
格特魯德，有件事我要告訴你
Gertrude, there's something that I wanted to tell you.
我要再次服役
I have reenlisted for active service.
我也期望
I expected it.
當我從戰爭中返回時
The moment I'm back from war,
我會處理好和朱迪斯的一切
I shall put everything in order with Judith.
那樣我就自由了
Thus should be free.
沒有你，我寧願...
I'd rather put a bullet in my head...
開槍自殺
than live without you.
你為什麼要這樣說？
Why do you say that?
格特魯德...
Gertrude...
有件事你得知道
There is something you should know.
朱迪斯有點想不開...
Judith has been making ominous remarks about...
如果我和她離婚，她要自殺
about committing suicide if I should try to divorce her.
我明白
I see.
我真不敢相信，但是...
I do not believe it, but...
愛是自私的
Love is a tyrant.
1915年7月 開羅，英國阿拉伯事物管理局
格特魯德...東亞事物大臣，恭喜啊
Gertie... Oriental secretary. Congratulations.
這就是他們發明的郵政快件
It's as if they invented the post foil.
- 這些都是你的員工？ - 是的
- All this is your staff? - It is.
你也成為高級顧問了，勞倫斯
You have become senior advisor, Lawrence.
你變成政治家了
You've moved into a political animal.
- 嚴格講，就像你說的，但是... - 什麼？
- Technically, I'm onto you, but... - What?
這裡沒有像我這樣的男人，也沒有像你這樣的女人
There are no men like me and no women like you, of course.
你已經成為了某種女王
You've become some kind of queen.
不，只是個想念自己男人的女兒而已
No, just a woman who misses her man.
你是說你的男人去參加偉大的戰爭了
You mean your officer who joined the glorious war.
是的
Yes, I do.
貝爾小姐...能靠近一點嗎？ 我們想讓
Miss Bell... could you get closer, please? We'd like to get
- 吉薩 皮拉米德進入鏡頭 - 丘吉爾先生！
- the Giza Pyramids in the frame. - Mr Churchill!
請不要動
Still, please.
丘吉爾先生，您對會議有什麼期望呢？
Mr. Churchill, what are you expecting from the conference?
先生們，讓我們來面對...
Boys, let's face it...
一個全新的阿拉伯世界
a new order in the Arab World.
丘吉爾先生，新的政策將在中東實施
Mr. Churchill, with this new emphasis on the Middle East,
放棄政策要針對印度實施嗎？
where does that leave off policy towards British India?
邱吉爾試圖說明這是大英帝國的一個新的成就
Churchill has tried to sell this as a new achievement of the British Empire.
- 還用問嗎？  - 好了，勞倫斯
- What else is it? - Come on, Lawrence.
我們沒辦法讓他們自治
We are not leading them towards autonomy.
這是阿拉伯國家的覺醒，這是他們的成就
It's the Arab nations who are awakening. This is their achievement.
當然
Of course.
大英帝國之獅
The Lions of the British Empire.
勞倫斯先生，請走這邊
Mr Lawrence, over this way please.
金字塔作為拍照的背景。先生們...
The pyramids in the background, for the photographers. Gentlemen...
要拍照，再往左邊一點，先生
You're having a shot. A little to the left, sir.
保持住，勞倫斯先生
Hold tight, Mr. Lawrence.
先生們，我們準備好了嗎？ 這張照片會很驚人的
Gentlemen, are we getting this camp? The shot is marvelous.
勞倫斯先生！
Mister Lawrence!
天那，先生們，你們拍到了嗎？
Marvelous. Boys, are you getting this?
就像這樣，再來一次，丘吉爾先生
One more like that, please, Mr. Churchill.
我的雪茄滅了
My cigar... my cigar went out.
真是世界末日啊
That is the end of the world.
再來一次，丘吉爾先生，你們看起來很壯觀
One more, Mr. Churchill. You're all looking splendid.
你們站在4000年的歷史面前
4,000 years of history upon you.
勞倫斯，閉嘴
Lawrence, shut up.
拿破侖在你之前說過
Napoleon said that before you.
好了，好極了！
Yes, all together now. Excellent!
我們在加利波利的損失很大
Our losses at Gallipoli are staggering.
澳大利亞遠征軍一天也損失了將近3萬人
and the Australian expedition force has lost 30,000 men in one single day.
將軍，這是保密的
General, this is classified.
我不管，明天整個世界都會打開窗戶大聲呼喊的
I don't care. By tomorrow, the whole world will shout of its window.
道蒂-懷利，指揮的戰鬥
Doughty-Wylie , who led the assault,
他已經得到了維多利亞十字勳章
has already been awarded the Victoria Cross.
你是說理查德？
Did you said Richard?
理查德 道蒂-懷利
Richard Doughty-Wylie ?
韋爾奇皇家火槍隊
Royal Welch Fusiliers.
維多利亞十字勳章是頒發給陣亡的英雄的
The Victoria Cross is only for fallen heroes.
正確
Correct.
我們是說，他已經在戰爭中陣亡了
We were told he was seeking death in combat.
我覺得這對他的妻子是個打擊
I think he has problems with his wife.
是的
Yes.
借過，謝謝
Excuse me. Thank you.
阿圖，沒有你我怎麼辦？
Fattuh, what I'd do without you?
我會一直跟隨著你，直到最後
I shall follow the lady to the end of the world.
親愛的日記...
Dear diary...
我內心的苦難，都源於你
in the afflictions of my heart, I am turning to you.
我的生命是否走到了盡頭
It is as if my life is ended,
我的愛是否是命中注定
as if love was not meant for me.
只有偉大的任務才能促使我繼續前進
And only the great task I have shoulded keeps me going.
開羅已經再次成為世界的中心
Cairo has became one of the centers of the world again.
我要開始我的新生活
And I'm starting a new life.
我的政治生涯
The life of a politician.
格特魯德...
Gertrude...
費薩爾王子請求和你會面
Prince Faisal has requested a meeting with you.
他似乎無處不在啊
He seems to be everywhere.
沙裡夫 赫斯的第三個兒子如何對付其他的兄弟呢？
How does the third son of Sharif Hussein deal with his brothers?
他的兄弟只對騎馬比賽感興趣
His brothers are only interested in horse racing.
格特魯德,我們不得不按規矩辦事
Gertrude, we have to play the game.
費薩爾很隱秘，狡猾，冷酷無情
Faisal is shrude, he's cunning, he's ruthless.
但是他似乎正是這時候的歷史舞台需要的人
But he seems to be the right one for this time in history.
- 讓我們坦誠的... - 坦誠相待是很危險的
- Let's be sincere... - It's dangerous to be sincere.
除非你也傻了
Unless you're also stupid.
英國的僑民早晚都是要過去的
England needs to get out its colonies sooner rather than later.
我接受上帝的旨意，很為我的國家擔心
I tremble for my country when I reflect that God is just.
我的兄弟費薩爾和我拜讀了你關於阿拉伯戰爭的文章
My brother Faisal and I have read your memorandum on the Arab war.
恭喜
Congratulations.
你表達了我們的心情
You do express our feelings.
沒有一個西方人能比你更瞭解貝都因人
No one in the Western world knows the heart of a Bedouin better than you.
貝都因人稱你為...
The Bedouins call you...
「高尚的女人」
"the noble lady".
我很榮幸
I am honored.
我們很同意他們稱你為「真實之母」
And we agree with those who call you "the mother of the faitful".
這是一個送給預言家妻子的頭銜，和平相處
A title given to the wife of the Prophet, peace upon him.
面對預言家的後代
In the face of two direct descendants of the Prophet
面對沙漠裡的人民
and in the face of the people of the desert,
我配不上這個榮譽
I am not worthy of that honor.
你的獵鷹...你的獵鷹配得上國王
Your falcon's... Your falcon's worthy of a king.
你很快就是國王了
You will soon be king.
統治誰呢？
Over whom?
統治我深愛的人民
Over the people I love.
是什麼讓一個英國女人如此深愛我們呢？
What makes an English woman love us so much?
我認識一個值得信賴的男人，是胡姆斯人
I have a trusted man, from Homs.
他...
He is...
他救過我的命
Well, he saved my life.
在沙漠裡救了我很多很多次
Many, many times in the desert.
他有個老母親，當她和他說話時
He has an old mother and when she speaks to him,
- 她有5個孩子 - 她說...
- she has five sons - she says...
阿圖...
Fattuh...
阿圖，我最信任的隨從
Fattuh, whom I entrust to bury me.
之後她說起天氣
And then she speaks of the weather,
她說起上帝...
she speaks of the God and...
為了孤獨...為了他...
and for that alone... for him...
你永遠在我心中
you will always have my heart.
現在，如果你允許，我要離開了
And now, with your permission, I will leave.
一路走好
Go in peace.
她怎麼知道我們會成為國王？
How could she know that we will be kings?
她是國王的創造者
She is the maker of kings.
她是沙漠女王
She is the crowned queen of the desert.
費薩爾和阿布杜拉成為了伊拉克和約旦的國王
格特魯德 貝爾幫助他們制定了國界
基於她的建議，英國幫助阿拉伯建立了自己的王國
格特魯德 貝爾沒有再結婚，1926年死於巴格達，就葬在那裡
貝都因人永遠深深的懷念這個外國人